Nick Osterbur: She does just introduce herself.
Nick Osterbur: All right. So Shagoon, could you introduce yourself?
Shagun Kaur: Sure.
Nick Osterbur: Yes.
Shagun Kaur: So, my name is Shagun Kaur. I am a Communication Studies faculty at De Anza College. I am also the Academic Senate Vice President, and the other hat that I wear is with Michelle. I am a former project facilitator for the state's OER initiative.
Shagun Kaur: And I want to hand it over to Michelle Pallotti, and the reason why she's here.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): Hi, good afternoon. My name is Michelle Pallotti. I'm the project director for the Academic Senate for California Community Colleges Open Educational Resources Initiative, or as was already said, simply OERI because that's just way too much.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): And in addition to our work around developing and sort of promoting OER, we also have gotten involved with
Michelle Pilati (she, her): things related to OER that colleges are struggling with, like, marking course sections, gathering data about course sections. We have reporting that we're supposed to do. Specifically, we're supposed to be tracking
Michelle Pilati (she, her): All of our course sections that…
Michelle Pilati (she, her): Basically for all of our courses we're supposed to be capturing whether or not they have a cost. And if they don't have a cost we are supposed to be capturing why they don't have a cost in reporting this. So if you can imagine all of our course sections somehow we have to get that information. As you probably know it's hard enough to get faculty to actually tell you what book they're using so that the bookstore can order it.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): So this is like this whole other level of trying to pull information together. And so that relates to the problem that we're going to be talking about.
Darren Kraker: And just real quick to clarify, by cost, you mean cost to the student, not cost to the university?
Michelle Pilati (she, her): Correct, correct, yeah. Cost of students. Cost of students, yes.
Shagun Kaur: So, to kind of preamble this, there is… there have been a couple of,
Shagun Kaur: legislation that has been passed. And one of the things that so imagine if I am the person doing it at my college, my job now is to ensure that for every single section at De Anza, which can run into the hundreds, I have to be able to trace back what is the cost of the instructional materials for that course. I have to trace back whether it meets a threshold of what we call low cost.
Shagun Kaur: which is a certain number, whether it is zero cost, and then if it is zero to the student, how is it being zero? Is it zero through the fact that I just bought a whole bunch of textbooks.
Shagun Kaur: and gave them to my students. It's zero through a program. It's zero because it's OER. I'm assuming everybody here knows what OER is. We just kind of walk into these spaces because we live and breathe this all the time.
Shagun Kaur: But if you need me to go back a little, I can go back a little.
Nick Osterbur: Is OER is Open Educational Resource?
Shagun Kaur: Yes, sorry, I remember you.
Nick Osterbur: No.
Shagun Kaur: How do you.
Nick Osterbur: That's okay. Can you expand on what that is and why it's important real quick?
Shagun Kaur: So part of that… Michelle, do you want to go back to trace the history of the OERI a little bit? And I think that'll make this a little clearer for Nick.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): Sure. Yeah. So open educational resources are educational resources that have an open license on them. So somebody still owns the copyright. But the open license basically says you can do all these other things with this resource, even though it does have a copyright. It does originally belong to someone. And so there's different levels of open license which doesn't really matter for this context, but just sort of understanding it.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): And what…
Shagun Kaur: But it was its genesis to open source, which you refer to. Yes.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): Right, right. Like, yeah, you said open source. When you say open source, we look at that as sort of the technology equivalent of the educational resources that are OER. And then the other sort of overlay of all of this is that in the California community colleges, a few years back, the governor passed $115 million our way to increase the availability of zero textbook cost courses. So
Michelle Pilati (she, her): Where by some mechanism, any of those possible mechanisms by which a course could get to zero to increase that. And so on top of needing to report about everything, we also had this huge investment to increase the number of sections that are zero. And I should point out our reporting is reporting that something has a cost.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): that's above a low… a low-cost threshold, or a cost that's below a low-cost threshold, not so much tracking the actual dollar amount. And… and then having to report that literally with our data… our data that we report
Michelle Pilati (she, her): It's capturing, you know, the number of students in classes, as well as the information about the textbooks that are or are not used.
Nick Osterbur: So… Sorry, go ahead.
Shagun Kaur: No, no, go ahead.
Nick Osterbur: I was going to say, I presume that right now this is a manually intensive process that takes a lot of time. Okay.
Shagun Kaur: Ding, ding, ding, ding, you hit the nail on the head. Not only is it a manually intensive process, there are multiple layers of pain points in this. Jennifer, you had a question.
Jennifer Bollinger: Oh yeah, quick question. So the reporting layer and then I think, Michelle, you also mentioned the bookstore too. So, and it's hard to get the faculty requisitions in. Does the bookstore, are they the ones that are doing the reporting or is like they do that as best they can and then get it over to you and then you report it back? I'm just trying to figure out like the chain of command.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): It's really complicated. And part of there's lots of different layers to this. So this data element that's the reporting that we're now having to do is something that's new. But meanwhile, a while back, we had legislation that required us to mark in our schedules our sections, which were no cost. The colleges were already
Michelle Pilati (she, her): trying to do something to get that information, but it tended to be very manual. Like, you would tell the bookstore what you tell the bookstore, and then separately from that, you would be reporting to someone that your section is no cost, if that happened to be the case. And so…
Michelle Pilati (she, her): Colleges have been trying to figure out how to make these things intersect. And part of the challenge is that there is no one source of truth and there's different entities gathering the information. So there might be a person who's identifying which sections are zero, then separately from that faculty are reporting to the bookstore, ordering their textbooks.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): And so there's just all these pieces that don't connect. I mean, I remember at my college where the tech people came and said, we're ready for the data element. I'm like.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): you are? Like, you figured out how to get the data? And they're like, no, we've just, we've got the data element, we know where to put it, we've got that information. Like, okay, you haven't gotten anywhere, because it's not even, it's not even clear whose job it is, which makes it a little bit even more complicated.
Jennifer Bollinger: Okay, that makes more sense.
Shagun Kaur: So, the typical… so, let me tell you the typical journey, Jennifer, and then you, Nick, and Darren can identify the pain points. So, this is what 90% of the 116 California community colleges do.
Shagun Kaur: Okay, so in terms of scale and scope of the work, just to put that in perspective, there is one hapless person who is sending out a survey, and that survey is then at the mercy of each faculty member to fill it to the best of their knowledge and intention, which assumes the fact that a faculty member
Shagun Kaur: the face of it, the faculty member should be able to tell the book, the cost of the book, and also, in some cases, correctly identify it as OER or not OER. Just because something is free online doesn't make it OER, and all of that jazz.
Shagun Kaur: At that point, all of that data is gathered by this person, and then input manually, Jennifer, into three areas to make it relevant for a student population. It has to be communicated to the bookstore, which is on the course schedule, so that when a student signs up for a course, they can
Shagun Kaur: click on that and see the required textbook or the associated material for that course. The state mandates that we should have the information of the course as zero or low on the schedule.
Shagun Kaur: before a student registration opens up, which means this has to happen before the quarter… the semester, or the… in our case, the quarter launches. That…
Shagun Kaur: is the first failure point. It never is possible, because these… it is so labor-intensive. So in many ways, when the information is most needed for a student to make an informed choice, whether they should sign up for a particular class based on the cost of the books.
Shagun Kaur: That choice is not available to them until after they register, which is the first failure point.
Shagun Kaur: After this data has been put in, and again, remember that this data is dependent on the number of faculty who actually fill it, and then on top of that, the faculty who fill it accurately.
Shagun Kaur: This person is then sent communicating this data manually through Excel spreadsheets, if you're lucky, to the bookstore, who is also updating the records.
Shagun Kaur: At this point, some faculty have gone to the bookstore separately and filled out their book requisition orders. The two processes are not connected because a bookstore generally does not have the incentive to aggressively seek this data.
Shagun Kaur: And also, it's usually a privately owned bookstore on most campuses, so the communication is lackluster.
Shagun Kaur: After this information is fed into the course schedule, which is one platform, it is also being fed back into the course management and the reporting data element for the state compliance.
Shagun Kaur: which is also manually inputted so that it can be back-ended, which is then gathered by someone who then reports it to the state. So these are the multiple pain points which are controlled manually, and the data entry and managing and code connection is happening back-end on Excel spreadsheets.
Shagun Kaur: Does that make… yeah, thank you. You're welcome, Jennifer. So that is the problem.
Shagun Kaur: for lack of a better word, Nick, to get back to your original charter for us, that we are trying to resolve. And the impact is that there's not a single college that has been able to automate this process.
Shagun Kaur: let me tell you the ideal scenario that would happen. If unicorns and rainbows were true, this is what an ideal situation would look like. An ideal situation would look like that as soon as a faculty member is given a class, or is assigned a class.
Shagun Kaur: He or she immediately puts in the book details right there on a small AI interface.
Shagun Kaur: Like a simple chatbot. And the chatbot is coded in with the data entry points, with… is coded with the XPTOL data that I put in the chat, which automatically allows the chatbot to determine the right element based on the input that the faculty has done on the front end. So the faculty never have to know, never have to commit a mistake.
Shagun Kaur: They just feed the information as they would with any user Google form, and in the back end, the AI takes care of it. And that data is then sent magically, and this is where your magic comes in.
Shagun Kaur: to the schedule so that it happens in real time, and the schedule marking is automated. It is then fed into the backend system, in our case, Banner, which then creates a MIS data entry column.
Shagun Kaur: And that way the data can just be simply exported and updated in real time as it is happening. And it accommodates for the fact that there might be a last-minute faculty change, there might be a book change, and so the system is built in for those kind of, failure points. That would be the ideal vision.
Shagun Kaur: And why we thought this would be a lovely problem for this.
Shagun Kaur: immensely talented group to handle.
Shagun Kaur: Does that give you a sense of what the… you know, we're just asking for the moon.
Nick Osterbur: Please.
Darren Kraker: In that ideal world, what are the minimum set of attributes that the faculty would have to enter?
Shagun Kaur: In that ideal world, they would have to enter their course section number, Which is unique.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): Wait, in a perfect world, in a perfect world, the faculty would be delivered something that or would be presented with a form that says, here's your name, here's the class you're teaching, here's the section number, and then provide the attributes that they that that only they can provide, which are what you're using a textbook. If you're using a textbook and it's a commercial publisher, you know, ISBN and all of that.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): if you're using a textbook and it's OER and it's no cost, where do your students get it? And then if it's low cost, or actually if it's free, but it's not
Michelle Pilati (she, her): It's OER. There's the different data elements. So it would prompt that it would get the faculty member to provide the information so that the appropriate XB12 code could be selected. As well as identifying that the section is zero textbook cost for the zero textbook cost marking and low textbook costs for marking it as low textbook costs. And also finding the commercial
Michelle Pilati (she, her): textbook information so that the bookstore has it. So the bookstore actually, ideally it would be, it would also push that information that the bookstore needs to the bookstore so the bookstore can make the bookstore orders.
Jennifer Bollinger: And what about taking it a step further with, I mean, this data exists because many faculty teach the courses over and over again. Is there a way to maybe even pre-populate it where the faculty is like, okay, accept this is all accurate, or do you want them to, you know, enter it in every semester?
Michelle Pilati (she, her): That would be amazing.
Shagun Kaur: Exc.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): I, I didn't, so.
Shagun Kaur: I do think that Michelle, who is much more polite than I am, is not saying. The minimum amount of data we can have faculty enter, the better, because they will make mistakes. So, if we can auto-populate many of the fields and reduce that margin of error, Jennifer, that will be ideal. In a quarter of school, and we are one of three in the state, California Community College System, where we are churning over four quarters rapidly.
Shagun Kaur: Pre-filled elements, which don't necessarily change, would be ideal. But even for the semester schools, I can think that would be a stress.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): No, if, yeah, and here's one thing that often are, well, some people don't understand. We don't roll section numbers over. It's not, it's like my sections aren't always 1178789 and you can't just roll that over. But if the system could recognize, oh, you, you selected this, you selected this textbook and it had these attributes last term, do you wanna do the same thing? And you could just say yes.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): That would be… That would be Nirvana. Yeah, that would be the ultimate. That really would be it.
Darren Kraker: Is the survey that's sent out public. Can you guys? Is that easy to like? Drop a link in the chat for that? Or is that something you'd have to go find.
Shagun Kaur: Every college has its own design survey. I can share the De Anza one with you, I can find a way to download and give it to you, that's not a problem. So… but…
Shagun Kaur: They're all trying to get at the same five questions in their own unique ways.
Shagun Kaur: And some do a good job of informing and educating faculty so that they can choose the right element. Some of us do not trust our faculty to make that choice, so the poor person then has to do
Shagun Kaur: solve the Tetris puzzle for each section one by one.
Shagun Kaur: So, it varies, but I can definitely share, Darren, what we do at our college. And maybe, through Michelle, we can show you a couple of other examples of other colleges. Now, there are many, many colleges that have figured out,
Shagun Kaur: The magic of dashboards and making the data present in a very pretty manner.
Shagun Kaur: Which is lovely, but it's secondary to first getting the data in the right places in the right way. So there exist dashboards that can take the data and marry it like a De Anza, if you… you know, because we're only asking for the moon, if I also wanted Venus, here's what else I would want.
Shagun Kaur: Somehow this magical data is then tied into our equity metrics and our equity data, so that at a section level.
Shagun Kaur: I, as an instructor, could go in and say, because I used OER, these are the, these are my, you know, marginalized populations that have actually benefited from it. That there would be a correlation between my equity and success metrics.
Shagun Kaur: And the fact that a low-cost book was used. That would be the ultimate. That would be above and beyond the scope of what we've given you. But essentially, having the data handy allows the second tier of analysis
Shagun Kaur: And impact to then come into play, which is not happening, because we don't have the data handy, and it's not always reliable.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): Well, and I would, so yeah, this is bad. You got to get us going and we could think of all kinds of things that would just be amazing. You know, we have systems to identify courses that are comparable to sort of say this course is public speaking, this course is intro psych, but we don't have anything captured with this data.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): that does that. So there are. There's this other attribute that you know. Intro psych has this identifying number. Everyone does. And if we actually had that, then we would. If we had that, and everyone was doing this, and we were, and they were all reporting their Xb. 12 data. But then also now, this additional data with information about what a particular course is.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): That would be so amazing because then we would actually be able to know how, and I'm picking, I teach psychology, she teaches com and public speaking and intro psych are both courses that are very, very commonly zero, but we literally don't have that system-wide data because all of our course data is not connected by our existing curricular structures that do connect it and completely ignore.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): I just went down such a rabbit hole, so please completely ignore.
Shagun Kaur: You… you might regret asking us, but we want to pause here for a minute, because we can go on for hours, as you can well imagine. This is what we live and breathe.
Nick Osterbur: Bye.
Shagun Kaur: So, questions?
Nick Osterbur: I'm going to peel it back and let's step back to the MVP aspect. And what data can we get a hold of to enable those students to be able to mock something like this up? And it sounds like…
Nick Osterbur: banner, like, is there a way to kind of faux or fake that banner integration? Is the bookstore piece important or not? And…
Shagun Kaur: So, I've offered up Diane's as a guinea pig, and which, when Anu approached me with this, and because it's, it's kind of housed in our district in a way, so we feel a sense of ownership, I'm happy to try and get the data points to you. What I can provide you is,
Shagun Kaur: And I'll have to speak to my college in terms of what information I need to protect on that. I could give you the survey as a sample, number one. I can also give you the raw, manually aggregated data of, let's say, two or three quarters to show you the range and scope of what information is obtained through the survey. And then maybe that can give your students a starting point of how that would get fed.
Shagun Kaur: Nick, so that could be two things I could provide you immediately. Now, what it looks like at the back end with Banner.
Shagun Kaur: I don't know how I could give you access to that, since you're not in the system.
Nick Osterbur: Yeah, Darren, do you have any experience with Banner?
Jennifer Bollinger: Well, you guys are running Banner on OCI now, right? Is that…
Jennifer Bollinger: Yeah, yeah.
Darren Kraker: Okay, I probably never used Banner. We used Moodle, we used a bunch of different ones, Blackboard, never Banner.
Jennifer Bollinger: Well…
Shagun Kaur: Those are learning management systems.
Jennifer Bollinger: Yeah, that would be like Instructure. Like, those are the equivalent to Instructure. What Shungun's talking about is ERPSIS.
Darren Kraker: Okay, yeah, well, we don't use Banner, it'.
Shagun Kaur: Yeah, and in fact, it should not actually be platform-specific, because it needs to be… if it's going to be implemented statewide, which is… you were talking about scope, Nick, of the project.
Nick Osterbur: And that'.
Shagun Kaur: And why it was worthwhile. Then, in some ways, we do need it to be kind of agnostic to the platform, because I know Black Banner is used at De Anza. Michelle, do you know what others are used? Rio Hondo uses…
Jennifer Bollinger: Colleague, PeopleSoft, People are.
Shagun Kaur: Oh, yeah.
Jennifer Bollinger: Workday now, yeah.
Shagun Kaur: Yes.
Shagun Kaur: So.
Shagun Kaur: I, I, yeah.
Shagun Kaur: I think what… I think the process of creating something that would integrate.
Shagun Kaur: and be able to push the same data, collect it at a central point, and push it to three different areas is really, I think, the core of the problem, or to quote you, Nick, the MVP.
Nick Osterbur: Okay.
Nick Osterbur: Are there any other data resources you can think of that would be valuable for this exercise, like the open education stuff? Is there a repo or API access to a database where name matching can happen, that sort of stuff?
Shagun Kaur: I wish there was a one-stop shop there. I mean, we are hoping in two years that most of it is housed in LibreText, which is kind of the state official partner for open, sources, and we can definitely kind of
Shagun Kaur: start to build from that, but they're usually top 3 players. There's OpenStax, there's Pressbook, there's LibreText, and…
Shagun Kaur: Michelle, am I missing something?
Shagun Kaur: Those are the top…
Michelle Pilati (she, her): The primaries, except for the, like, the one-offs, like the anthropology, things like that. Yeah.
Shagun Kaur: So, I mean, I don't know, Nick, if that would be helpful to share that with you. So, I'm making a list.
Nick Osterbur: Yes.
Shagun Kaur: So you want to get access to the survey, you want to get access to some raw data, so that you can start to play around with it.
Shagun Kaur: And you want… you want links to these OER sources? Is that what I heard from you say?
Nick Osterbur: I think so, yeah.
Darren Kraker: I'm on the oercommon.org, like, is there… is that the right source for… no.
Shagun Kaur: No.
Darren Kraker: To the right URL, to the open.
Shagun Kaur: Yeah, OER Commons, I mean, if somebody was just going to OER Commons to find something, there would be other issues of articulation that would fly for me. There might be Skills Commons, but that's kind of reaching into those special areas, right?
Michelle Pilati (she, her): They're also referatories. They're not a place that holds resources. They just point you to someplace else. So something will be in commons, but it actually lives somewhere else.
Shagun Kaur: Thank you.
Michelle Pilati (she, her): It's.
Shagun Kaur: I think between LibreText and OpenStax, we should probably have 90% of it covered, no? Michelle?
Nick Osterbur: Can a human find out if a resource is open just by doing one Google search?
Shagun Kaur: 95% of the time, yes.
Nick Osterbur: Okay.
Nick Osterbur: That's really good to know.
Shagun Kaur: Yes.
Nick Osterbur: The machine machines can do Google search now, so.
Shagun Kaur: Okay.
Shagun Kaur: Yeah, no, Claude does a pretty good job with mine.
Shagun Kaur: Tragically, not so much.
Nick Osterbur: Okay, what else?
Nick Osterbur: Any questions, Darren? Jennifer?
Shagun Kaur: If you didn't realize, we were going for shock and awe.
Nick Osterbur: And ha!
Nick Osterbur: Appreciate that.
Nick Osterbur: I guess on the diversity of the equity dashboard thing, are there any supplementary data sets there that would help the team kind of mock that for that experience?
Shagun Kaur: I can reach out to my IR person. We use Precision Campus at De Anza, because we are one-off, but we can also see if Christina would be able to kind of share some of the backend, right?
Michelle Pilati (she, her): say to because a conversation with Alex could probably help you to understand how they how they are connecting the course, the student data within the course to make all those kind of connections.
Shagun Kaur: So maybe the next step should be to have a conversation with Alex in the room.
Shagun Kaur: Yeah, we can, we can try and make that happen. Alex is a.
Shagun Kaur: is an IR person at Chabot College who has done some amazing stuff with collecting the data from the, portals like Banner and front-facing it on a dashboard that is interactive. And his work is open source. In fact, it's been shared widely. We can, we can…
Shagun Kaur: We can first share the data with you and then see if he's available for a meeting, if that would help the team understand how it all works better.
Shagun Kaur: Like, because he might be able to answer some of your technical questions better than we can.
Nick Osterbur: Okay.
Nick Osterbur: All right, we're almost at time. Any last comments before we stop the recording?
Shagun Kaur: Please make this happen. You, in terms of impact, that is 3 million students and 116 California community colleges that will thank you.
Nick Osterbur: Okay. Okay. Highly scalable.
Nick Osterbur: Sounds good. Alright, HiSeen.